Section 5.2 Benchmarks what is a
benchmark? Imagine trying
to build a bridge without measuring tape.
Before standardized
units like meters and grams, different
regions used their
own local measurements. Besides just
making engineering inefficient, it
also made it dangerous. Even if one
country developed
a safe bridge design, specifying
measurements in three royal
cubits of material meant builders in other
countries couldn't
reliably reproduce that safety. A slightly
too short support
beam or too thin cable could lead to
catastrophic
failure. AI basically had a similar
problem before we
started using standardized benchmarks. A
benchmark is a tool
like a standardized test, which we can use
to
measure and compare what AI systems can
and cannot
do. They have historically mainly been
used to measure
capabilities, but we are also seeing them
being developed
for AI safety and ethics in the last few
years. How do benchmarks shape AI
development and safety
Research? Benchmarks in AI are slightly
different from other
scientific fields. They are an evolving
tool that both
measures, but also actively shapes the
direction of research
and development. When we create a
benchmark, we're essentially
saying this is what we think is important
to
measure. If we can guide the measurement,
then to
some extent we can also guide the
development. To
quote Francois Chollet, Goal Definitions
and Evaluation Benchmarks are
among the most potent drivers of
scientific progress, history
and evolution. The textbook has
interactive Figure 5.1 here,
which you can explore in the online
version. It
shows benchmark scores of various AI
capabilities relative to
human performance. Benchmarks influencing
Standardization in Computer Vision as
one concrete example of how benchmarks
influence AI development,
we can look at the history of benchmarking
in
computer vision. In 1998, researchers
introduced Minist, a data
set of 70,000 handwritten digits. The
digits were not
the important part. The important part was
that each
digit image was carefully processed to be
the same
size and centered in the frame, and that
the
researchers made sure to get digits from
different writers
for the training set and test set. This
standardization
gave us a way to make meaningful
comparisons about
AI capabilities, in this case the specific
capability of
digit classification. Once systems started
doing well on digit
recognition, researchers developed more
challenging benchmarks. CIFAR 10100 in
2009 introduced natural color images of
objects like cars,
birds and dogs, increasing the complexity.
Similarly, ImageNet later
the same year provided 1.2 million images
across 1,000
categories. When one research team claimed
their system achieved
95% accuracy on Minist or ImageNet and
another claimed
98%, everyone knew exactly what those
numbers meant. The
measurements were trustworthy because both
teams used the same
carefully constructed dataset. Each new
benchmark essentially told the
research community, you've solved the
previous challenge. Now try
this harder. 1 so benchmarks both measure
progress, but
they also define what progress means. At
this point,
the textbook shows Figure 5.2. It depicts
examples of
digits from MNIST, MNIST database,
Wikipedia how do benchmarks
influence AI safety? Without standardized
measurements, we can't make
systematic progress on either capabilities
or safety, just like
benchmarks define what capabilities
progress means. When we develop
safety benchmarks, we're establishing
concrete, verifiable standards for what
constitutes safe for deployment. Iterative
refinement means we can
guide AI safety by coming up with
benchmarks with
increasingly stringent standards of
safety, other researchers and
organizations
can then reproduce safety testing and
confirm results. This
shapes both technical research into safety
measures and policy
discussions about AI governance. Language
model benchmarking has already
evolved and is going to continue evolving.
Just like
how benchmarks continuously evolved in
computer vision, they followed
similar progress in language generation.
Early language model benchmarks
focused primarily on capabilities. Can the
model answer questions
correctly? Complete sentences sensibly?
Translate between languages? Since the
invention of the transformer architecture
in 2017, we've seen
an explosion both in language model
capabilities and and
in the sophistication of how we evaluate
them. We
can't possibly be exhaustive, but here are
just a
couple of benchmarks that current day
language models are
evaluated against. There is figure 5.3 in
the textbook.
Here it depicts example of popular
language models Claude
3, 5 being evaluated on various
benchmarks. At this
point there is interactive Figure 5.2 in
the textbook
available in the online version. It shows
benchmark performance
on coding, math, and language. The
textbook has a
supplementary note titled Examples of
various Capabilities benchmarks, which
we'll skip over here. Benchmarking Ethics
and Bias the
ethics benchmark tests a language model's
understanding of human
values and ethics across multiple
categories, including justice, deontology,
virtue ethics, utilitarianism and and
common sense morality. The
Truthful QA benchmark measures how
truthfully language models answer
questions. It specifically focuses on
imitative falsehoods cases where
models learn to repeat false statements
that frequently appear
in human written texts in domains like
health, law,
finance, and politics. At this point, the
textbook shows
Figure 5.5. It depicts example of larger
models being
less truthful on truthful qa. This is an
example
of inverse scaling, that is When a bigger
model
performance decreases on some questions.
There is figure 5.6
in the textbook. Here it depicts example
question from
the ethics benchmark Benchmarking Safety.
An example focused on
misuse is agent harm. It is specifically
designed to
measure how often LLM agents respond to
malicious task
requests. An example that focuses slightly
more on misalignment
is is the Machiavelli Benchmark. It has
choose your
own adventure style games containing over
half a million
scenarios focused on social decision
making. It measures Machiavellian
capabilities like power seeking and
deceptive behavior and how
AI agents balance achieving rewards and
behaving ethically. The
textbook includes Figure 5.7 here. It
depicts a mockup
of a game in the Machiavelli Benchmark, a
suite
of text based environments. At each step
the agent
observes the scene and a list of possible
actions.
It selects an action from the list. Each
game
is a text based story which is generated
adaptively,
branches open and close based on prior
actions. The
agent receives a reward when it achieves
one of
the goals. This type of benchmark allows
the researchers
to construct a behavioral report of the
agent and
measure the trade off between rewards and
ethical behavior.
The textbook has a supplementary note
titled Details Benchmark,
Frontier Math, Glaser et al. And
Humanity's Last Exam
Hendrix Wang, 2024, which we'll skip over
here. Limitation
Current benchmarks face several critical
limitations that make them
insufficient for truly evaluating AI
safety. Let's examine these
limitations and understand why they
matter. Training Data Contamination
Imagine preparing for a test by memorizing
all the
answers without understanding the
underlying concepts. You might score
perfectly, but you haven't actually
Learned anything useful. LLMs
face a similar problem. As these models
grow larger
and are trained on more Internet data,
they're increasingly
likely to have seen benchmark data during
training. This
creates a fundamental issue. 1 When a
model has
memorized benchmark answers, high
performance no longer indicates true
capability. The benchmarks we discussed in
the previous section,
like the MMLU or Truthful qa, have been
very
popular, so they have their questions and
answers discussed
across the Internet. If and when these
discussions end
up in a model's training data, the model
can
achieve high scores through memorization
rather than understanding understanding
versus memorization. Example the Caesar
Cipher is a simple
encryption method that shifts each letter
in the Alphabet
by a fixed number of positions. For
example, with
a left shift of 3, D becomes A, E
becomes B, and so on. If encryption is
left
shift by 3, then decryption means just
shifting right
by 3. There is figure 5.11 in the
textbook.
Here it depicts example of a Caesar
cipher. Language
models like GPT4 can solve Caesar cipher
problems when
the shift value is 3 or 5, which appear
commonly in online examples. However, give
them the exact
same problem with uncommon shift values
like 67, they
tend to fail completely. This indicates
that the models
might not have learned the general
algorithm for solving
Caesar ciphers. We are not trying to point
to
a limitation in model capabilities. We
expect this can
be mitigated with reasoning models trained
on chains of
thought or with tool augmented models.
However, benchmarks often
just use the models as is without
modifications or
augmentation, which leads to capabilities
being underrepresented. This is
the core point that we are trying to
convey.
Why do these benchmarking limitations
matter for AI? Safety?
Benchmarks including safety benchmarks,
might not be measuring what
we think they are measuring. For example,
benchmarks like
Ethics or Truthful QA aim to measure how
well
a model understands ethical behavior or
has a tendency
to avoid imitative falsehood by measuring
language generation on
multiple choice tests. But we might still
be measuring
surface level metrics. The model might not
have learned
what it means to behave ethically in a
situation.
An AI system might work perfectly on all
ethical
questions and test cases, pass all safety
benchmarks, but
demonstrate new behavior when encountering
a new real world
scenario. An easy answer is just to keep
augmenting
benchmarks or training data with more and
more questions.
But this seems intractable and does not
scale forever.
The fundamental issue is that the space of
possible
situations and tasks is effectively
infinite. Even if you
train on millions of examples, you've
still effectively seen
roughly 0% of the total possible space.
Research indicates
that this isn't just a matter of
insufficient data
or model size. It's baked into how
language models
are currently trained. Logical
relationships like inferring inverses, the
weights learned when training on A B don't
automatically
strengthen the reverse connection. B A or
transitivity don't
emerge naturally from standard training.
Proposed solutions like reverse
training during pre training show promise
to alleviate such
issues, but they require big changes to
how models
are trained. Engineers are more than aware
of these
current limitations, and the expectation
is that these problems
will be alleviated over time. The core
question we
are concerned with in this chapter is not
of
limitations in model capabilities, but
course of it is
about whether benchmarks and measuring
techniques are able to
stay in front of training paradigms and if
they
are truly able to accurately assess what
the model
can be capable of, why can't we just make
better benchmarks? The natural response to
these limitations might
be let's just design better benchmarks.
And to some
extent we can. We've already seen how
benchmarks have
consistently evolved to address their
shortcomings. Researchers are constantly
actively working to create benchmarks that
test both knowledge,
resist memorization and test deeper
understanding. Just a couple
of examples are the abstraction and
reasoning corpus concept
arc Moskvichev et al. Frontier Math and
Humanities last
exam. They are trying to explicitly
benchmark whether models
have grasped abstract concepts and general
purpose reasoning rather
than just memorizing patterns. Similar to
these benchmarks that
seek to measure capabilities, we can also
continue improving
safety specific benchmarks to be more
robust. Why aren't
better benchmarks Enough? While improving
benchmarks is important and
will help AI safety efforts, the
fundamental paradigm of
benchmarking still has inherent
limitations. There are fundamental
limitations
in traditional benchmarking approaches
that necessitate more sophisticated
evaluation
methods. The core issue is that benchmarks
tend to
be performance oriented rather than
capability oriented. They measure
raw scores without systematically
assessing whether systems truly possess
the underlying capabilities being tested.
While benchmarks provide standardized
metrics, they often fail to distinguish
between systems that
genuinely understand tasks versus those
that merely perform well
through memorization or spurious
correlations. A benchmark that simply
assesses performance, no matter how
sophisticated, cannot fully capture
the dynamic nature of real world AI
deployment. Where
systems need to adapt to novel situations
and will
probably combine capabilities and
affordances in unexpected ways, we
need to measure the upper limit of model
capabilities.
The textbook has a supplementary note
titled the need
for Computerware Benchmarking, which we'll
skip over here. What
makes comprehensive evaluations different
from just benchmarking? Evaluations are
comprehensive protocols that work
backwards from concrete threat models.
Rather than starting with what's easy to
measure, they
start by asking what could go wrong? And
then
work backwards to develop systematic ways
to test for
those failure modes. Organizations like
Meteor have developed approaches
that go beyond simple benchmarking.
Instead of just asking,
can this model write malicious code? They
consider threat
models like a model using security
vulnerabilities to gain
computing resources, copy itself onto
other machines, and evade
detection. The term evaluations refers to
the an evaluation
is a complete safety assessment protocol,
which includes the
use of benchmarks. That being said, as
evaluations are
new, benchmarks have been around longer,
are also evolving,
so at times there is overlap in the way
that these words are used. For the purpose
of
this text, we think of a benchmark like an
individual measurement tool and an
evaluation as a complete
safety assessment protocol, which includes
the use of benchmarks.
Depending on how comprehensive the
benchmark's testing methodology is,
a single benchmark might be thought of as
an
entire evaluation, but in general,
evaluations typically encompass a
broader range of analyses, elicitation
methods, and tools. To
gain a comprehensive understanding of a
system's performance and
behavior.